Mommy?
媽媽？
Mommy, where are you?
媽媽，你在哪裡？
Suzume, are you up yet?
鈴芽，你起床了嗎？
Yes.
起來了
There's a high-pressure system over Kyushu...
九州上空氣壓升高...
- We expect blue skies and... - Looks delicious!
- 預計會迎來晴天... - 我要開動了！
Don't forget your lunch today.
別忘了帶午餐
Okay.
知道了
Oh, and Suzume...
對了，鈴芽...
I'm going to be late tonight,
今晚我會晚點回來
so figure out dinner on your own.
你自己解決晚餐吧
Do you have a date, Tamaki?
阿姨，你要去約會嗎？
Then, take all night!
如果是的話，不回來也行！
It's overtime.
我是要加班
The "Fisherman Experience" event prep.
為了準備“漁業體驗”
See you later.
我出門了
Beautiful...
好美...
Hey...
請問...
you.
你...
Do you know of any ruins in this area?
你知道附近有沒有廢墟？
Ruins...?
廢墟？
I'm looking for a door.
我在找一扇門
Well, there's a little abandoned town
那裡有個無人的小鎮
over by that mountain...
就在那座山後面
I see.
好的
Thank you.
謝謝你
Huh?
蛤？
Did you watch yesterday's livestream?
你看了昨天的直播嗎？
It was amazing!
太精彩了！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Good morning.
早安
Mornin', Aya.
阿雅，早安
Why's your face all red?
你的臉怎麼那麼紅？
It is!? Seriously?
真的嗎？我的臉？
Yeah.
嗯
What's up?
怎麼了？
I forgot something!
我忘了東西！
What!? You're gonna be late...
什麼!? 就快要遲到了
Why...
為什麼...
did I...?
我...
[TONAMI RESORT VISITOR'S GUIDE]
【門波度假村觀光指南】
[DO NOT ENTER]
【請勿進入】
This is it, right?
應該是這裡吧？
I can't think of any other "ruins."
好像沒有其他廢墟了
Excuse me?
不好意思
Hello?
有人嗎？
Mister?
剛才的帥哥？
I feel like...
我覺得...
we've met somewhere before.
好像在哪裡見過你
Am I totally stalking him right now?
這樣看起來是在搭訕嗎？
I should go back.
還是回去吧
He said something about a door.
剛才他好像說了一扇門
Huh?
蛤？
What is this?
這是什麼？
What!?
什麼!?
Why...?
為什麼會這樣？
Huh?
蛤？
What?
這是什麼？
It's cold.
好冰啊
What the heck is going on!?
這是怎麼回事？
Creepy!
好可怕！
There you are.
你終於來了
To what do we owe the pleasure?
大駕光臨
Lunch from your aunt?
阿姨準備的便當？
I can taste the love from here.
充滿了愛心
Right...
對了
Hey, you know those ruins by Kaminoura?
你們知道上之浦的廢墟嗎？
The old bathhouse district.
就是那個古舊的溫泉街
Really?
又怎樣？
I remember it's in the mountains, right?
我記得是在山裡面
What about it?
那裡怎麼了？
There's this door...
那裡有一扇門...
Never mind.
還是算了吧
For real!?
你不是吧！？
- Gonna leave us hanging? - Spill the beans!
- 吊我們胃口嗎？ - 快說！
Hey, is that a fire?
你看，那裡失火了嗎？
Where?
哪裡？
Over by the mountains.
就在山的另一邊
Huh? Where?
蛤？哪裡？
Look at the smoke!
那裡冒起了煙！
What are you talking about?
你在說什麼？
Do you see anything, Aya?
阿雅，你有看到嗎？
Nope.
沒有
But...
可是...
Is it from the fields?
是田園嗎？
It's right there.
就在眼前
W-What!?
什麼？！
[EARTHQUAKE WARNING]
【地震警報】
An earthquake?
地震？
Intensity 4.0!
強度4級！
Do you feel it?
你感覺到了嗎？
Yeah, it is...
嗯...
Oh, it's shaking.
開始震動了
Hey, an earthquake.
有地震
Really?
是嗎？
I'm wide open!
前面沒人！
Let's go!
快進攻！
What was that?
那是什麼？
Think we're okay.
好像沒事了
Is it over?
結束了嗎？
That was nothing.
好像沒什麼
That was a little scary...
嚇死我了
The warning was a bit much.
真是虛驚一場
Hey...
喂
Look...
你們看…
over there.
那裡
What are you talking about?
你在說什麼？
Suzume, are you okay?
鈴芽，你沒事吧？
They can't see it...?
她們看不到嗎？
Hey, Suzume!
等一下，鈴芽！
Daddy!
爸爸！
Why can't anyone...?
為什麼大家都...
What IS that thing?
那個究竟是什麼？
Don't tell me...
難道…
It can't be!
不會吧！
There's no way!
不可能的！
It's that door!
是那扇門！
It's him!
是那個人！
What are you doing!?
你在做什麼？
Get out of here!
快離開這裡！
Are you all right?
你沒事吧？
What now?
這是什麼？
This is...
情況...
...not good.
不妙
[Earthquake warning] - Dammit!
【地震警報】 - 不好了！
Watch out!
小心！
Get away from here!
快離開這裡！
Dammit...
可惡…
[Earthquake warning]
【地震警報】
Why are--?
你幹什麼？
You need to close this, right?
這裡要關起來吧？
O Divine Gods who dwell beneath this land...
令人敬畏的神明啊
You have long protected us for generations...
古老的祖先之地啊
Thy mountains and rivers...
請容許我把您
- that we have long called our own... - (Dad! C'mon, hurry!)
- 恩賜的山河 -（爸爸！快來！）
- (Over here!)
-（這裡！)
What's...!?
什麼！？
(Haven't been to a bathhouse in a while.)
（好久沒來澡堂了）
(Mom, let's take a bath again!)
（媽媽，我們再洗一次！）
(Honey, are you having another drink?)
（老公，再來一杯嗎？）
(Let's come again next year. On a family trip!)
（明年我們再來就當是家庭旅行!)
It's closed!
關上了！
I return to thee!
全部都奉還於你！
What was that?
剛才的是什麼？
The Keystone was supposed to keep this place sealed.
原本這裡是被要石封印住了
Why did you come here?
你為什麼來到這裡？
How can you see the worm?
你又怎麼能看到地龍？
Where is the Keystone!?
要石去了哪裡？
Worm?
地龍？
Stone...?
什麼石頭？
What are you talking about?
你在說什麼？
This place became a Gate.
這裡變成了後門
The worm comes through the Gate.
地龍從後門來到了這裡
Thank you for helping me.
總之，謝謝你的幫助
Now, forget everything you saw here and go home.
把這裡看到的都忘了，快回家去吧
But...
可是...
Wait! Your arm!
等一下！你的手臂！
[MIYAZAKI BROADCASTING]
【宮崎廣播】
That was a pretty big earthquake.
地震挺大的
Look at these shingles...
你看這些殘骸...
I think we got off pretty light.
我們算是僥倖逃過一劫
Please go upstairs.
請上樓等我
I'll get the first aid kit.
我去拿藥箱
That's really not--
不用了
If you won't go to the hospital,
如果不去醫院
at least let me bandage it.
至少讓我幫你包紮
Is he some kinda man-baby?
是大男人自尊心嗎？
[HOW TO BECOME A NURSE]
【如何成為一名護士】
A child's chair.
兒童的椅子
Around 1:20PM this afternoon
今天下午1點20分左右
there was an earthquake in Miyazaki
宮崎縣發生地震
with a recorded magnitude of 6.3.
地震強度為6級
There is no risk of a tsunami at this time.
現在並無海嘯危險
We do not have any information regarding injuries--
也沒有任何傷亡報告
You know your stuff.
你倒是挺懂的
My mom was a nurse.
媽媽以前是護士
But first...
話說...
I have a ton of questions.
我有很多問題
Figures.
我就知道
You said "worm." What did you mean?
剛才你說的地龍是什麼？
The worm is a giant force that dwells beneath the Japanese islands.
地龍是存在日本地底巨大的力量
It has no rhyme or reason.
它不需要任何目的或理由
Yet, it rages and shakes the land if disturbed.
就能發狂，搖晃整片土地
But you just beat it, right?
不過，剛才你把它抑制了吧？
I only shut it away temporarily.
我只是暫時阻止了它
If we don't seal it with the Keystone, it'll appear again.
如果不用要石把它封印起來，它會再出現的
You mean there'll be another earthquake?
你是說會再發生地震嗎？
It's my job to stop that from happening.
我的工作是阻止災難發生
Your job...
工作...
Hey, who exactly are yo--
你到底是...
Thanks for patching me up.
謝謝你的幫助
My name's Souta Munakata.
我的名字是宗像草太
I-I'm Suzume Iwato.
我是岩戶鈴芽
A cat...?
貓咪？
Oh my gosh, this kitten's a toothpick.
天啊，怎麼骨瘦如柴
One sec.
等一下
You must've been starving.
你一定餓壞了
That earthquake was scary, huh?
地震很可怕吧？
So cute.
好可愛
Want to become my cat?
要讓我收養嗎？
Yeah.
嗯
Suzume...is kind.
鈴芽…好善良
I like you.
我喜歡你
You...are in the way.
你這傢伙...礙事
W-W-Whaaa--!?
什麼！？
Souta? Where are you?
草太？你在哪裡？
What the...
這是...
...hell!?
搞什麼鬼！？
Whaaaaa--!?
你是...
S-Souta?
草太？
Suzume...
鈴芽...
What's happening?
我是怎麼了？
Is this your doing!?
是你做的吧？
Come back here!
不要走！
Dammit...!
去你的！
What the--!?
到底怎麼了？
This can't be happening!
太不可思議了！
No no no no!
不會的，不會的！
Oh, Suzume.
鈴芽！
Tamaki!
阿姨！
Sorry, stepping out!
借過，我要出去一會！
Where are you going?
你要去哪裡？
I came home early, worried about you.
我擔心你，所以提早回來了
The earthquake!?
地震！？
You didn't pick up your phone.
你都不接電話
Sorry! Missed it.
對不起！我沒注意到
But, I'm okay.
不過，我沒事
H-Hey...
等一下...
Suzume! Answer me!
鈴芽！早點回來！
Hey, a kitty!
小貓！
What IS that?
那是什麼？
Excuse me!
借過一下！
What is even happening right now?
到底是怎麼回事？
Hey, Suzume!
喂，鈴芽！
HEY!
你好！
Where...
你到底...
...are you going!?
...要去哪裡？
What the--!?
這是什麼？
Ack!
豁出去了！
I'm SO, SO sorry!
不好意思！
Thank you very much for your patience.
感謝您的耐心等候
We have been given clearance to depart.
我們已經獲得通行許可
We are now disembarking from the dock.
郵船即將離港
Hey, did you see that?
你有看到嗎？
- Yeah, I did. - What the heck was that?
- 嗯 - 那究竟是什麼？
A toy?
是玩具嗎？
[NO PETS] You see that chair?
【禁止攜帶寵物】 你看到那張椅子嗎？
Very impressive.
好逼真啊
Where...
你到底...
did you go!?
去了哪裡？
My gosh...!
真要命！
Why do you run!?
你幹嘛要逃跑！？
What did you do to me!?
你對我做了什麼？
What are you!?
你是什麼東西？
Answer me!
快說！
Oh no!
不好了！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
See you.
後會有期
Whaaaaat!?
什麼！？
Like I said...
我跟你說了...
I'm spending the night at Aya's.
今晚在阿雅的家過夜
I'm sorry.
抱歉
I'll be home tomorrow.
明天一定回家
Now wait just one moment, Suzume.
鈴芽，等一下
You can stay over,
過夜沒有問題
but why is the first aid kit in your room?
可是，你的房裡怎麼會有藥箱？
Did you have someone over?
有人來過嗎？
I don't even want to think about it, but...
我不想胡思亂想，可是...
Are you seeing some good-for-noth--!
你是不是跟什麼小混混...
NO!
不是的！
No boys! I'm hanging up!
不說了！我要掛了！
Did you see that runnin' chair, missy?
你有看到會跑的椅子嗎？
No.
沒有
Souta.
草太
This ship will reach Ehime by morning.
郵船早上就會抵達愛媛
Looks like the cat's ship is heading there too.
貓咪逃上的船也是
I see.
好的
I got some bread.
我買了麵包
Thanks.
謝謝
But I'm not hungry.
可是，我不餓
Okay.
嗯
Um, why are you a chair?
為什麼你變成了椅子？
Apparently, that cat placed a curse on me.
好像是那隻貓對我下了咒
A curse!?
下咒？
Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
Does it hurt?
有哪裡不舒服嗎？
I'm fine.
我很好
You're warm.
好溫暖
Still, I have to figure this out.
不過，我還是得想辦法解決
Souta, there's something bothering me.
草太，我有一件事想說
A relic in the ruins...?
廢墟的石像？
That's the Keystone!
那就是要石！
You removed it?
是你拔出來的？
Removed...?
拔出來？
Of course...
原來...
That cat is the Keystone!
那隻貓就是要石！
How dare it leave its post.
它竟敢擅離職守
What do you mean?
是什麼意思？
You set the Keystone free, and now it's cursed me.
你釋放了要石，現在我被它詛咒了
Oh no...
不會吧...
I'm so sorry, I...
我很抱歉...
What should I do?
我應該怎麼做？
No.
不是你的錯
It's my fault for not finding the door sooner.
都是我應該更早發現那扇門
This isn't on you.
你不必自責
But...
可是...
Suzume, I'm a Closer.
鈴芽，我是一位閉門師
A "Closer"?
閉門師？
I close the open doors so that disaster won't spread.
為了阻止災難發生，我必須關閉所有敞開的門
I travel across Japan doing that.
就因如此，我遊遍整個日本
It's our job as Closers.
這就是閉門師的工作
You're hungry, right?
你餓了吧？
Eat up.
快吃點東西
We must turn the Keystone back and banish the worm.
我們要把貓咪變回要石，然後把地龍封印著
Surely then, I'll return to my body.
到時候，我就能變回原樣
So, don't worry.
所以，你不用擔心
Tomorrow, you're going home.
明天，你就回家吧
Mommy?
媽媽？
Mommy!
媽媽！
Where are you!?
你在哪裡？
Souta?
草太？
Do you always sleep like that?
睡得不省人事
My heart's pounding.
我的心跳好快
Thank you very much for riding the Shikoku Orange Ferry today.
感謝您今天搭乘四國橙橘郵輪
- Man it's hot. - Finally!
- 好熱啊 - 終於到了!
- You're goin' to Osaka? - It's been a while.
- 你去大版嗎? - 好久沒來了
Yeah, but I'll spend the night somewhere.
嗯，可是會在別處過夜
On behalf of the entire crew, we hope to see you again.
我僅代表全體員工，希望您再次搭乘我們的郵輪
Suzume?
鈴芽！
Finally, you are up!
你終於起來了！
You wouldn't wake up,
你一直不醒來
I was beginning to think this was all a dream.
讓我覺得這一切都是夢
I was asleep?
我睡著了？
Never mind.
算了吧
Now, how do we find that cat?
我們要怎麼找到貓咪？
We should ask around the harbor first.
不如先在港口附近問人
But where are we?
可是，這裡是哪裡？
Hey, you!
你...
It looks like...
這裡好像是...
the edge of Ehime?
愛媛縣的邊角？
Wow, we came a long way.
哇，我們長途跋涉來到這裡
Get on the next ferry, and you can make it home tonight.
坐上下一班郵船，晚上之前還來得及回家
- You should-- - Oh no!
- 你應該... - 糟糕！
What is it!?
怎麼了？
[OMG! I FEEL LIKE I'M IN "WHISPER OF THE HEART"]
【太可愛了！似乎在《聽聽我的心》裡】
Hey, a white cat.
小白貓
It's so cute!
好可愛！
A kitten?
是小貓？
What's your name?
你叫什麼名字？
Who are you?
你是誰？
And you are?
請問你是？
Perhaps "Daijin"?
叫你大臣吧？
Daijin?
大臣？
You do seem pretty fancy.
看起來挺氣派的
[IT'S SO ADORABLE... SITTING NEXT TO ME.] [#WithDaijin]
【好可愛...就坐在我身邊】 【#與大臣同在】
[POSTED]
【已上傳】
[TWEETED]
【已推】
This is SO him, isn't it?
這個是它吧？
How could this be...
怎麼會這樣...
[LOOK WHO I MET]
【瞧我遇到了誰】
[GETTING OFF THE TRAIN]
【下車了】
[CONDUCTING!]
【貓咪車長】
[SNACK TIME]
【吃零食】
[INSTAGRAM-ABLE]
【上鏡】
[LOOKING SLY...!!] "Daijin"?
【聰明伶俐】 “大臣”？
I mean he does kind of...
它的確是長得有點...
He's moving by train.
它在搭乘火車
I have to go after him.
我要去找它
Thanks for everything, Suzume.
謝謝你，鈴芽
This is goodbye.
再見了
Get home safely.
小心回家
Umm...
呃...
Your family's going to worry if you don't go home.
你不回去，家人會擔心的
It's fine. They let me make my own choices.
沒事的，我的家人都很開放民主
This could be very dangerous.
我們要面臨的可能很危險
It's not safe for you to follow me.
你不可以跟著來
I think you've got bigger problems right now.
草太，你的問題比較大吧
Look. [I JUST SAW SOMETHING CRAZY!]
你看 【我剛看見超神奇的！】
[I SAW IT TOO!]
【我也看到了！】
[MYSTERY GIRL AND MOVING CHAIR]
【神秘女孩與移動椅子】
[NEW ROBOT FROM BOST*N DYNAMICS...!?]
【最新機器人！？】
[SEND ME INFO!]
【求訊息！】
Oh no...
不會吧...
It's dangerous for you to walk in public.
你在大庭廣眾下很危險
Someone's gonna catch you before you catch the cat.
貓咪還沒找到，你就先被抓起來了
Guess I've got no choice...
看來我是別無選擇
Suzume...
鈴芽...
Until we find the Keystone...
我需要你的幫忙
I'll need your help.
一起找到要石
My pleasure.
這是我的榮幸
["DAIJIN" APPEARS ON TANGERINE FARM #WithDaijin]
【“大臣”出現在橘子園#與大臣同在】
Souta.
草太
Oh crap!
糟糕！
Whaaa--!?
什麼!?
Hold that side.
快抓住另一邊
Oh, right.
嗯
No way...
不會吧...
You're a lifesaver!
你是我的恩人！
Thanks so much!
太謝謝你了！
It was nothing.
我沒做什麼
You're like a wizard.
你太厲害了
How'd ya do that?
你是怎麼辦到的?
My body reacted before I could think... I guess?
我想是...身體的自然反應吧？
Well, amazin' either way.
怎麼說，你太厲害了
I'm Chika. A junior in high school.
我叫千果，高中一年級生
Me too!
我也是！
I'm Suzume.
我是鈴芽
Your uniform... You're not from 'round here, are ya?
你的制服…看來你不是這裡的人吧？
Oh, right.
嗯
You came all the way from Kyushu to look for a cat!?
千里迢迢到九州來找貓！？
Is it yours?
是你養的貓咪嗎？
Not exactly.
也不算是
Hey, this photo...
根據照片...
I think it's near here.
應該是這裡附近
What's the matter?
怎麼了？
Suzume?
鈴芽？
Sorry, I just remembered something.
對不起，我得走了
Hey, whaddya mean?
是什麼事情？
Suzume!?
鈴芽！？
Can the worm show up anywhere?
地龍在哪裡都能出現嗎？
The Gate in this area has opened.
這裡的後門打開了
We need to close it fast.
要趕緊把它關起來
We're not going to make it at this rate.
我們這樣是來不及的
Oh no!!
那如何是好？
HEY!
喂！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Chika?
千果？
Dunno what's goin' on, but you're in a rush, yeah?
我不知道發生了什麼事，可是你趕時間吧？
Get on!
快上車！
You sure this is the way?
你確定是這裡嗎？
Few years back, there was a landslide.
幾年前發生了土崩
There's nothin' past here.
前面什麼都沒有
It's abandoned?
是廢墟嗎？
That's perfect. Keep going!
太好了，拜託你快點！
Will there be another quake?
會再發生地震嗎？
We must close the door before the worm falls to the earth.
地龍墜落地面之前，要把門關上
Or else...!
不然...
[DO NOT ENTER]
【請勿進入】
Here's fine!
這裡就行了！
Thanks so much, Chika!
太感謝你了，千果！
Huh? S-Suzume...?
什麼嘛？鈴芽...
Suzume, you've done enough.
鈴芽，你已經幫了很多
Hey, wait--! Souta!
等一下！草太！
It's too dangerous.
前面太危險了
Go back with that girl.
跟那女孩一起回去吧
You can't go with that body!
你還是一張椅子呢！
I have to.
我沒有退路了
[KASUGA MIDDLE SCHOOL]
【春日中學】
The school's become a Gate.
學校變成了後門
Dammit.
可惡
I can't even...!
我連這個都...!
No!
糟糕！
It's falling.
開始往下墜落了
Souta!
草太！
Suzume!?
鈴芽！?
Are you not afraid to die!?
你不怕死嗎？
I'm not!
我不怕！
Suzume?
鈴芽？
You lock the door.
快把門鎖上
Close your eyes and think of the people who lived here.
閉上眼睛，想著從前住在這裡的人們
The keyhole will appear.
鑰匙孔就會出現
You're telling me this now!?
你現在才跟我說這些!?
Please! I can't do it!
拜託你！我自己沒有辦法
Close your eyes!
閉上雙眼！
Now feel all the emotion that should be here.
感受這裡的情感
Listen to their voices.
傾聽他們的聲音
(Mornin'!)
（早安）
(I've got exams tomorrow.)
（明天還有考試呢）
(Man, it's hot!)
（天氣好熱！）
(We can't lose the next match!)
（下一場比賽絕對要贏！）
(Come hang out after you graduate.)
（畢業後也要回來）
O Divine Gods who dwell beneath this land...
令人敬畏的神明啊
You have long protected us for generations...
古老的祖先之地啊
Thy mountains and rivers...
請容許我把您
that we have long called our own...
恩賜的山河
Now!
趁現在！
I return to thee!
全部都奉還於你！
We did it, Suzume.
鈴芽，太好了
You just prevented an earthquake.
你阻止了地震發生
Really?
是嗎？
I can't believe it...
我不相信...
I did it!
我居然辦到了！
We make a great team!
我們太厲害了！
Suzume, you're amazing.
鈴芽，你真棒
Another Gate will open.
另一扇後門即將開啟
The Keystone.
要石
Wait!
等一下！
Did he open the door?
是它打開後門的嗎？
You're in Ehime?
你在愛媛？
Suzume, you said you were staying at Aya's yesterday.
鈴芽，你說你昨天在阿雅的家過夜
"A little vacation"...?
“微旅行”？
Not funny at all.
一點都不有趣
I had better see you home tomorrow.
明天你一定要回來
- Where are you staying tonight? - Minoru, we got a table.
- 今晚你住在哪裡？ - 阿稔，該去喝一杯了
Go ahead. I'll catch up.
你先去吧，我待會就去
I'll invite Tamaki.
也看看小環要不要一起去
That's NOT what I'm talking about!
我不要跟你說這些！
What about school?
學校怎麼辦？
Suzume going through a rebellious phase?
鈴芽正在叛逆期嗎?
Anyway!
不管怎樣！
Tell me where you're staying tonight.
你快跟我說今晚住在哪裡
And, I really hope you're alone, young lady.
我希望你真的是自己一個人
Minoru...
阿稔...
Something on my face?
你在看什麼？
Oh, Shige made a reservation...
阿茂訂了位子
Huh? Where did--!?
呃？他人在哪裡？
Honestly...
真是的...
[SORRY FOR HANGING UP]
【對不起掛斷了電話】
[I'M GOOD!]
【我很好！】
[I PROMISE TO COME HOME SAFELY!]
【我答應會安全回家！】
[PLEASE DON'T WORRY!]
【請不用操心！】
[*BOW*]
【*鞠躬*】
[READ]
【已讀】
Yes?
有事嗎？
I brought ya dinner.
我帶晚餐來了
Wow, thank you!
哇，謝謝你！
Mind if I join ya, Suzume?
我可以和你一起吃嗎？
Not at all!
當然沒問題！
Could you give me a sec?
不過，可以等我一下嗎？
What do we do?
現在該怎麼辦？
You two enjoy yourselves.
你們慢慢享用吧
Looks like this body doesn't get hungry.
這張椅子似乎都不會肚子餓
[INN - AMABE]
【天邊旅館】
Let's eat!
我要開動了！
It tastes sooo good...
太好吃了...
Um, are you cryin'?
你在流眼淚嗎？
It just tastes so good.
因為太美味了
You must've been starvin'.
你一定是餓壞了
For some reason we just had a ton of customers today.
今天的客人特別多
Sorry to keep you waitin'.
不好意思讓你久等了
No, not at all!
不要那麼說！
You're the one putting me up tonight.
是你收留了我
With a bath, yukata, and food!
還可以洗澡，有浴衣穿，還有美食！
[NEW MESSAGE]
【新訊息】
Ugh.
啊
Who is it?
是誰？
My aunt.
我的阿姨
Oh man...
天啊...
She seriously needs a date.
她應該快找個男朋友
Your aunt's single?
你阿姨還單身？
How old is she?
她幾歲了？
About 40, I think?
差不多四十歲？
She's really pretty, though.
長得還算漂亮
It's just the two of us.
我們兩個人住在一起
She's my guardian.
她是我的監護人
Sounds complicated.
聽起來挺複雜的
Not really.
一點都不會
But sometimes...
只是有時候...
I feel like I've stolen her most precious years.
我覺得自己剝奪了她寶貴的青春
Especially lately.
尤其是最近，特別那麼覺得
You sound like her ex-boyfriend.
怎麼聽起來像前男友說的話
Oh my gosh!
真的！
I wish she'd just leave the nest already.
我希望她能早點脫單
Speakin' of ex-boyfriends...
說起前男友...
Suzume, you ever dated anyone?
鈴芽，你有交往過嗎？
Me? No...
我嗎？沒有...
Mmm-hmm, that's the best thing for ya.
那就好，那就好
Nothin' good comes from datin' guys.
男人沒有什麼好東西
Were you going out with someone, Chika?
那你呢？你有男友嗎？
You wanna hear?
你想知道嗎？
- Not again!
- 又來了！
Why don't you clean the bath next?
不如去打掃澡堂吧？
You're kidding!
騙人的吧！
He DIDN'T...!
他真的那樣做？
Oh, totally.
就是說嘛
Not just that...
還不止呢
Whaaa--!? For real?
什麼!? 不會吧？？
Right? Boys are dumb.
我就說嘛...男人真是笨蛋
I got to go there again today thanks to you.
今天多虧了你，讓我又回到那裡
My middle school was over there.
我的中學就在那裡
After the landslide a few years ago they abandoned the whole area.
幾年前的土崩後，那裡就被廢棄了
Hey, Suzume.
鈴芽
What were you doin' there?
你去那裡是為了什麼？
Covered in mud and all...
全身泥土髒兮兮的...
And what's with that chair?
還有，那張椅子呢？
Who exactly are ya?
你又是來這裡做什麼？
That chair...is a memento from my mom.
椅子是...母親留給我的紀念
But now...
可是現在...
Sorry, it's hard to explain.
抱歉，有點難以啟齒
Suzume, you're like a wizard.
鈴芽，你好像魔術師
Full o' secrets.
神神秘秘的
But why do I feel like...
可是，為什麼我總覺得...
you're doing somethin' really important?
你背負著重責大任？
Thank you, Chika!
謝謝你，千果！
Yeah, I think I'm doing something important, too!
嗯，我也覺得我正在做一件大事！
Modest much?
自吹自捧就免了吧！
Some people just refuse to wake up.
有些人就是怎麼都叫不醒
Who? Your BF?
誰啊？男朋友？
I don't have one!
我才沒有男朋友！
I mean in general.
我只是說說罷了
If they won't wake up...
如果真的不起來
just give 'em a kiss.
就給他一個吻
Wha--!?
什麼？
I heard you're headin' home?
你要回家了？
Yes, I am!
是的！
Thank you so much for everything.
謝謝你的照顧
You're welcome anytime, y'hear?
隨時歡迎你再來
Thank you!
謝謝！
Hey, check it out!
快看這個！
This guy's amazin'!
太神奇了！
It is unknown where this kitty came from,
這隻來歷不明的小貓
but he's crossing the cables of a suspension bridge.
在吊橋上行走
Uhhh...
欸...
Ain't that somethin'?
是不是很了不起？
Hey, Souta!
草太！
Wake up already!
快起來！
Ugh.
真是的!
Wait.
等一下
Where's your mouth?
嘴巴呢？
Suzume...?
鈴芽?
Good morning.
早安
What is it?
怎麼了？
Don't "What is it" me!
別問我了
- Look, it's Daijin. - This kitty is creating a lot of buzz...
- 你看，是大臣 - 小貓造成了不少騷動...
- What's he trying to do?
- 它到底想做什麼？
Gods follow naught but their own whims, so...
神明就是捉摸不定
Gods?
神明？
That bridge leads to Kobe.
吊橋的另一端是神戶
We should--!
我們也應該...
Suzume.
鈴芽
You're leavin' soon, right?
你要走了嗎？
Yeah, just getting dressed.
嗯，正在準備
Perfect.
太好了
Use these, if ya want.
不嫌棄的話，這個給你
Yup. Suits ya better than me.
嗯，果然比較適合你
Ya stuck out in your uniform with that chair.
校服加上那張椅子太顯眼了
Chika...
千果
How can I ever repay you?
我要怎麼回報你？
Don't worry nothin' 'bout it.
別客氣了，小事一樁
Come visit sometime?
有空就來玩吧
Yeah.
嗯
I promise.
我一定會來的
[TO KOBE]
【往神戶】
Suzume...
鈴芽...
You need to be clearer about what you want.
你要更清楚的表態
Like waving your arms or something.
要揮手或做什麼的
YOU do it and people will be shocked and stop.
不如你來做，他們肯定會嚇呆停車的
Chairs shouldn't be moving.
椅子不應該會自己亂動
Thank goodness.
太好了
You DO get it.
原來你也有自知之明
Can we go by bus?
巴士能去嗎？
The next bus is six hours from now.
下一班車是六小時後
Suzume.
鈴芽
You said this chair was a memento of your mother?
你說這張椅子是母親留給你的？
Yeah.
嗯
Why does it only have three legs?
為什麼只有三隻腳？
I was so young, I don't really remember.
當時我年紀還小，已經不記得了
But, I lost this chair once.
不過，我曾經遺失過這張椅子
When I found it, a leg was missing.
找回來的時候，就少了一隻腳
Where you headed?
你要去哪裡？
Won't be any buses for a while.
巴士不會那麼快來的
Sounds fun.
真好
A little soul searching?
一個人的旅行
Going to downtown Kobe?
神戶市沒問題嗎？
That would be amazing.
嗯，謝謝你
Got it.
好的
We were visiting their grandma's and were on our way back to Kobe.
我們去探望婆婆，現在要回去神戶
You really lucked out.
你真走運
- Mom, look at this! - What is it?
- 媽媽，你看這個！ - 是什麼？
Stop touching her stuff!
不要亂動姐姐的東西！
Okaaaay.
好
Sorry.
真不好意思
It's fine.
沒事的
Why are they staring at your stuff...?
他們為什麼一直盯著你的東西？
It's just a chair.
只是一張椅子
I see.
是嗎？
Still staring...
目不轉睛的...
[EHIME]
【愛媛縣】
[TOKUSHIMA]
【德島縣】
[KOBE]
【神戶】
Careful!
小心一點！
Don't spill anything.
不要打翻了
Keep her chair nice and clean.
別把椅子弄髒了
- I know! - You bet'cha!
- 我知道！ - 沒問題！
Didn't know you could see it from here...
我不知道從這裡可以看到...
The amusement park.
遊樂場
An amusement park?
遊樂場？
Over there, on the mountain.
那裡，在山上
My folks would take me there when I was little.
小時候，父母常帶我去
But things went downhill.
可是，因為遊客銳減就關閉了
Now, they don't even have the money to tear it down.
連拆除的錢都沒有
There's lots of lonely places like that these days.
最近有很多這種讓人傷感的地方
I don't believe it...
不會吧...
The kids' daycare just texted
托兒所剛傳來簡訊
saying they had to close today.
說今天臨時休息
Hey, knock it off!
不要鬧了！
Ugh, I have to open the shop soon.
我還要趕去開店
Gotta find someone...
得找一個人...
Oh!
哦！
Hm?
什麼？
Huuuuuh!?
我嗎！？
[KYUNOMIYA SUJI STRIP MALL]
【九宮筋商店街】
Umm...
呃...
What do you want to play?
你們要玩什麼呢？
House!
扮家家酒！
Let's make curry!
我們來煮咖哩！
Ready...
預備...
GO!
開始！
Whaaa--!?
什麼!?
Don't eat those!
那個不可以吃！
Whoever empties it first wins.
誰先抽完就贏
Ready? GO!
預備? 開始！
Stop that!
快住手！
You're Mt. Fuji, 'kay?
姐姐來扮富士山，好嗎？
Ready? GO!
預備？開始！
I don't think...
我覺得...
...I'm cut out for kids.
我真的沒有育兒天份
You need help...
真沒辦法...
What the--!?
這是...？
Heeeeey! Isn't it amazing?
你們看！很厲害吧？
What a super cool toy.
這玩具好神奇
[BAR HARBOR] Whoooooa!
【港口酒吧】 哇！
Me too! Me too!
輪到我了！我也要！
My turn next!
也讓我坐坐！
Not you.
不可以！
It talked!
它會說話！
P-Pretty cool, huh?
很神奇吧？
It's a chair-shaped robot...with built-in AI?
擁有最新人工智慧的椅子機器人
What's its name?
它有名字嗎？
Souta.
草太
Souta, what's tomorrow's weather!?
草太，明天天氣如何？
Souta, play music!
草太，播放音樂！
Souta, a word game!
草太，來玩文字遊戲！
Souta, are the stocks up today!?
草太，今天股市如何？
Souta's not that smart, so...
草太沒那麼聰明...
What was that, Suzume?
鈴芽，你說什麼？
It spoke again!
它又說話了！
Running away from home?
離家出走嗎？
I mean, I did it when I was a kid too.
小時候，我也做過
When you're at that age,
到了那個年紀
the town, your parents... it's suffocating.
身邊的環境和父母...都讓你喘不過氣
So--
所以...
We're not talking about you.
我不想知道你的事
Right.
也對
Where is she going?
她到底要去哪裡？
What did I do wrong?
我到底做錯了什麼？
She keeps putting me off.
她什麼都不跟我說
Won't even tell me where she's staying tonight.
就連今晚住哪裡也不說
What about her phone's GPS?
手機的定位呢？
I don't have access.
我沒有權限
What about her bank account?
銀行戶口呢？
Is it linked to her phone?
有連接手機嗎？
Where is she?
她在哪裡？
She's in Kobe...
在神戶...
Kobe?
神戶?
[TRANSACTION HISTORY] That's a long way from home.
【使用記錄】 離這裡好遠啊
I can't let her be alone anymore...
我不能讓她獨自一人...
Um, Tamaki?
小環？
If there's anything else I can do--
有什麼我能幫忙的...
Minoru.
阿稔
I'm taking the day off tomorrow.
明天，我要請假
What?
什麼？
Then, I'm taking the day off, too.
那我也要請假
Why? You need to work.
為什麼？你繼續工作
Right...
說的也是
Suzume.
鈴芽
Can you come down?
你能下來嗎？
Okay!
好的
Whoa!
哇！
Rumi, you look gorgeous.
瑠美小姐，你好漂亮
Like a different person, huh?
判若兩人吧？
The kids all good?
孩子們都還好嗎？
Yup. Sound asleep.
嗯，都已經睡著了
Then, you can give me a hand over here.
那你能來幫忙嗎？
It's never this crowded...
今天客人怎麼那麼多...
Ma'am.
媽媽桑
She's the help?
你找她來幫忙？
Yep!
是的
What!?
什麼!?
Welcome!
歡迎光臨！
You don't have to work the floor.
你不用留在外場
Got it.
是的
- Wash these. Quick. - O-Okay.
- 把這些洗乾淨，快一點 - 是的
- Ice, please! - Coming!
- 冰塊！ - 好的！
- Two wine glasses. - Huh?
- 兩個酒杯 - 什麼？
- No, the ones next to those. - Right.
- 旁邊的那些 - 好的
[NOW HIRING HOSTESSES] Welcome!
【招聘女性兼職】 歡迎光臨！
Suzume, three hot towels.
鈴芽，來三條毛巾
Okay!
好的
Ow!
好燙！
Where's the bottle?
瓶子在哪裡？
- For Sasaki. - R-Right...
- 上面寫著“佐佐木” - 是的...
♪ I had too much to drink. And it was all your fault...
♪ 都是你的錯，讓我醉意萬分
♪ How endearing it is from a tender young lady...
♪ 嬌柔的女生是多麼讓人疼惜
You're awfully young, aren't you?
你還很小吧？
Come drink with an old lady.
來陪我這老太婆喝一杯
Why don't we sing a duet?
不如陪我唱歌吧？
Really? So ya like 'em young, do ya?
不是吧？老牛還想吃嫩草？
Why, thank you!
多謝惠顧！
Miki? You got us there.
美琪？讓你逮到了
Oh well.
你來也不錯
What do you mean, "Oh well"?
你是什麼意思？
Hey, Daijin!
嘿，大臣！
Another glass!
再來一杯！
Wha--!?
什麼？
Daijin, you big spender.
大臣，你真闊氣！
You go!
太好了！
This isn't happening...
不可能吧...
U-Umm... That seat over there.
那邊位子上的...
Hm? Oh, he's a first-time customer.
誰？那位客人是第一次來這裡
C-Customer--
客人...
He's quiet but getting along with regulars already.
感覺很文靜，可是已經跟熟客混熟了
Um, but doesn't he look a bit...
他看起來不像...
...cat-like?
貓咪嗎？
You think so?
你覺得像嗎？
Seems pretty refined to me.
看起來挺有品味的
Seriously!?
不會吧？
Oh, welcome!
歡迎光臨！
Sorry, but gotta go!
對不起，我要出去一下
Souta!
草太！
It's Daijin--!
是大臣！
Hey, just what are you--!?
你到底想做什麼？
Suzume. How you doin'?
鈴芽，你還好嗎？
What?
什麼？
Look.
你看
Over there.
那裡
The worm.
地龍出現了
Daijin!
大臣！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
We need to go.
我們得走了
Yeah!
嗯！
Is it an earthquake?
是地震嗎？
Huh? Really?
蛤？真的嗎？
Hey, Miki. Where's Suzume?
美琪，鈴芽人呢？
It's the amusement park!
是遊樂場！
[NOTICE OF CLOSURE]
【關閉通知】
[THANK YOU FOR 40 AMAZING YEARS]
【感謝惠顧40年】
The Ferris wheel!
摩天輪！
It's become a Gate!
變成了後門！
Souta, look!
草太，你看！
Daijin.
大臣
I'm going to catch Daijin and turn him back to a Keystone!
我要抓到它，把它變回要石！
While I do that, you...
你就...
Yeah.
嗯
Close the door and lock it.
把後門關起來鎖上
I can do this.
讓我來
Get the door!
拜託你關門了！
Okay!
好的
I can make it!
我可以的！
My body...
我的身體...
I can really move!
我可以靈活移動!
I'm getting used to this!
我已經習慣了
I won't fail again.
不會再失敗了
Suzume.
鈴芽
You're goood!
你好棒！
Daijin...!
大臣！
Today, you will turn me back!
今天，我一定要變回原樣！
Look! The lights are on.
你看！燈都亮了
Why?
為什麼？
Wasn't it abandoned?
不是已經廢棄了嗎？
What?
什麼？
Wh-Wh-Whoa--!
等一下！
Seriously!?
不會吧？
Mom...?
媽媽？
Become the Keystone, and seal that worm!
快變回要石，把地龍封印起來！
The Eastern Pillar alone will not hold.
只靠東邊的柱子是撐不住的
Can't...
我不要
Why!?
為什麼！？
I've entrusted this duty to you.
我已經把責任託付於你了
What does that mean?
你是什麼意思？
You go away.
你消失吧
Daijin's gonna play with Suzume.
讓我來跟鈴芽在一起
With Suzume?
跟鈴芽一起？
Suzume!
鈴芽！
What happened, Suzume!?
發生了什麼事，鈴芽！？
What's going on?
你到底怎麼了？
What do you see?
你在看什麼？
Suzume!? Come back.
鈴芽！？快回來
You mustn't go in!
你不能進去！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Suzume, you're inside a Ferris wheel!
鈴芽，那裡是摩天輪！
Wake up! You're going to fall!
快醒過來！你要掉下去了！
Dammit.
不好了
O Divine Gods who dwell beneath this land...
令人敬畏的神明啊
You have long protected us for generations...
古老的祖先之地啊
Thy mountains and rivers...
請容許我把您
that we have long called our own...
恩賜的山河
- (Whoa, it's so high up!) - that we have long called our own...
-（哇，好高啊！） - 恩賜的山河
- (Cool!)
-（太酷了！）
(Don't have too much fun now.)
（不要玩得過火了）
(We should come here again, together!)
（我們下次再來！）
(This is our anniversary. Let's come back.)
（今天是我們的紀念日，我們下次再來）
(An amusement park on our first date is so cliché!)
（第一次約會在遊樂場好老土！）
(Daddy, let's come back again!)
（爸爸，我們下次再來！）
Suzume! Come!
鈴芽！快過來！
Souta?
草太？
O Divine Gods who dwell beneath this land...
令人敬畏的神明啊
You have long protected us for generations...
古老的祖先之地啊
Thy mountains and rivers...
請容許我把您
that we have long called our own...
恩賜的山河
Now!
趁現在！
I return to you!
全部都奉還於您！
Where's Daijin?
大臣呢？
Gone. Again.
又讓它逃了
Let's go inside.
我們進去吧
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I was so scared!
好可怕！
You were amazing.
你表現的很好
Thank you.
謝謝你
Suzume...
鈴芽...
What were you looking at, beyond the Gate?
你在後門的另一邊看到了什麼？
A bright night sky filled with stars and fields...
充滿星星的夜空和田園...
The Ever-After.
是常世
So you can see it...!?
你能看得到常世！？
"Ever-After"?
“常世”？
This world's other half, where the worm dwells.
世界的另一端，也是地龍存在的地方
And, where all time exists simultaneously.
是所有時空同時存在的地方
I could see it, but I couldn't go in.
我能看得見，可是卻進不去
The Ever-After is where all souls go to rest.
常世是亡者的休憩地
It's not somewhere the living can reach.
不是生人可以去的地方
Not a place we're supposed to go.
那裡不是我們應該去的
The troublemaker's back.
小搗蛋回來了
Suzume, where were you!?
鈴芽，你去了哪裡？
Oh, um... I'm sorry.
呃...對不起
You had me worried sick! Running off at this hour.
這種時間突然溜出去，你知道我多擔心嗎？
Well, she's all right, isn't she?
她不是沒事回來了嗎？
But--!
可是...！
How many times have we run away from home?
我們也都不是過來人嗎？
Why don't we have a bite for now.
我們先來吃點東西吧
Sorry...
對不起...
How about fried udon?
炒麵怎麼樣？
Yeah! With a sunny side up on top.
好啊！再加上太陽蛋
And tuna-mayo!
還要美乃滋鮪魚！
Yeah.
嗯
And you, Suzume?
鈴芽，你呢？
We actually put potato salad on top.
我的家是放馬鈴薯沙拉
- Say what? - On fried udon?
- 什麼？ - 在炒麵上嗎？
O-M-G.
天啊
Think about the calories.
簡直卡路里爆表
Sooo hungry.
好餓啊
Thanks for the meal!
我要開動了！
Delish!
真好吃！
I'll gain some weight.
肯定又要發胖了
Needs a beer!
配上啤酒更好！
Should we?
要來一杯嗎？
After drinking all night?
你還要喝？
Sure, why not?
有關係嗎？
Join us, Souta.
草太，你也一起吃吧
Didn't expect the potato salad, though.
沒想到馬鈴薯沙拉還蠻搭的
- H-Hey! - I'm making this for my boyfriend.
- 喂！ - 我也要做給我男友吃
What boyfriend?
你又沒有男友
I'll have one in no time.
我很快就會找一個的
What's with that chair?
那是什麼椅子？
Adorable.
好可愛
A kid's chair?
給孩童用的嗎？
Why are you on it?
你怎麼坐在上面？
A Kobe souvenir...?
為了紀念神戶？
You're not making any sense.
完全聽不懂
They must've thought you were weird.
她們一定覺得你是怪咖
Really?
是嗎？
Do you travel like this all the time?
你是這樣一直到處流浪嗎？
Not all the time.
也不是
I have a flat in Tokyo.
我在東京有房子
After college, I plan to be a teacher.
大學畢業後準備當教師
What!? You're a university student?
什麼!? 你是大學生？
Yeah?
不可以嗎？
And...a job!?
你還要工作！？
What about THIS job!?
這份工作呢？
Being a Closer has been in my family for generations.
閉門師是代代相傳的祖業
I'll continue that.
我會繼續的
But it doesn't put food on the table.
可是卻不能養活自己
I see...
原來如此
But it's an important job.
即使你的工作非常重要
Most important jobs, people shouldn't see.
重要的工作，還是眼不見為淨
I need to get back into my own body.
我要盡快變回原來的樣子
So I can continue this and become a teacher.
才可以繼續當閉門師和教師
But... I'm already...
可是，我已經...
Perhaps, I'm...
或許...
already...
我已經...
It's getting farther.
越陷越深
The light grows dimmer.
燈火越來越暗
And so do the voices.
聲音也越來越遠
My body...
我的身體...
My mind...
我的心都在慢慢消失
It's so...
我覺得...
Cold.
好冷
I'm so cold.
越來越...
Cold...
冷...
Am I...
我是不是...
Is this where...
難道這就是...
I meet my end?
我的結束嗎？
Souta?
草太？
Souta!?
草太！？
Good morning.
早安
Took you long enough.
你總算起來了
Hey, there's another photo of Daijin.
又有大臣的照片了
See?
你看
Suzume.
鈴芽
Did...
剛才...
Did you just do something to me?
你對我做了什麼？
Nope.
沒有啊
- The Chugoku Expressway south towards Okayama... - I was counting on you to help me at the bar tonight, too.
- 前往岡山的中國高速正在塞車... - 本來還希望今晚你也來酒吧幫忙
Here, this is for you.
這個給你
You look even more like a runaway child now.
現在看起來更像離家出走了
Rumi, thank you so much for everything.
瑠美小姐，謝謝你
Mmhmm.
嗯
Just be sure to send word to your guardian.
你要聯絡家人
I will.
我會的
Ah, crap!
糟糕！
I totally forgot about Tamaki.
我徹底把阿姨忘了
55...unread messages?
55封...未讀訊息？
She's coming to get me?
她要來接我回去？
Suzume, you can make the next train.
鈴芽，我們還趕得上下一班車
Buy a ticket. Hurry!
快去買車票！
The bullet train?
搭新幹線嗎？
We know where Daijin is, so...
我們知道大臣在哪裡，所以...
It's the quickest way, right?
這是最快的方法吧？
To Tokyo, though?
去東京？
That'll take all my savings.
我的儲蓄快沒了
You better pay me back, Mr. College Man.
你這個大學生，最好要把錢還給我
I gotcha.
知道了
Souta, look!
草太，你看！
What is it?
怎麼了？
This train is SO fast.
新幹線，速度真快！
Cool!
太厲害了！
Yeah...it's fast.
的確很快
We will soon arrive at Atami. The doors on the...
列車即將抵達熱海，車門將在...
Souta, did we just...
草太，我們是不是...
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Did we just miss Mt. Fuji?
我們是不是錯過了富士山？
Look!
你看！
Why didn't you say something!?
你怎麼不提醒我？
Ahh, right...
是的
I wanted to see it...
我好想要看...
Sorry...
對不起...
We'll soon be arriving at Tokyo.
列車即將抵達東京
Tokyo. This is the final stop.
東京，這裡是終站
That way, Suzume.
鈴芽，這裡
Okay!
好的
Right.
也對
Left.
往左
Go up.
往上
Train on the left.
左邊的列車
Run!
快上車！
Get off, next stop.
下一站下車
Wha--!?
什麼？
Why do I feel like your horse?
為什麼我要讓你牽著鼻子走？
Before Daijin, there's a place I want to go.
找大臣之前，我想要去一個地方
Could you make a call?
你能幫我打電話嗎？
Welcome!
歡迎光臨！
Um, my name is Iwato.
你好，我姓岩戶
I just phoned...
剛才撥過電話...
Oh, right.
是的
Souta's relative.
我知道
I heard about you.
你是草太的親戚
Here's the key to his room.
這是他的房間鑰匙
Room 301.
301號房
Take your time.
請慢走
Well, aren't you popular, Souta?
草太，你很受歡迎吧？
When is he coming back from his trip?
他什麼時候旅行回來？
It's a bit lonely without him.
他不在，總覺得很寂寞
"He's so sweet and cute!"
“他又善良又可愛!”
And gorgeous.
還很帥呢
Don't take them seriously...
她們只是在開玩笑
Really...?
真的嗎？
Welcome.
請進
Scuse me...
打擾了
I want to look something up.
我想要找一點東西
See the cardboard box on top of the shelf?
你看到書架上的箱子嗎？
Grab it for me.
能幫我拿下來嗎？
Sure.
嗯
Oof...
看我的...
Souta, can I step on you?
草太，我能踩在你上面嗎？
Ask that BEFORE you do it!
不要先斬後奏！
[SECRET ARTS OF CLOSERS VOL.1]
【閉門師密傳 第一章】
Is this...
這個是...
the worm?
地龍嗎？
Yeah.
是的
And this is the Keystone.
這就是要石
The Western Pillar.
西邊的柱子…
And the Eastern Pillar.
和東柱的柱子
Then does that mean...
所以，要石有...
...there are two Keystones.
有兩個要石
Disasters that couldn't be contained by closing the Gate
關閉後門不能阻止的災難
were sealed away using the Keystones.
需要利用要石封印起來
So...
所以...
The locations change era to era.
位置會隨著時代改變
The Keystone from Kyushu is now running around as Daijin.
九州的要石就是大臣，現在到處竄走
Yeah.
嗯
The other Keystone is here.
另一個要石就在這裡
In Tokyo.
東京
Keeping the worm's head at bay.
現在抑制著地龍
What I want to know is exactly where...
我想要知道的是...
Where in Tokyo it is.
它到底在東京的什麼地方
Apparently, there's a huge Gate there too.
那裡顯然也有一扇巨大的後門
It opened 100 years ago and decimated the Kanto region.
一百年前，後門打開後引起了關東大地震
And was shut by the Closers of that time.
那時候，閉門師成功關上了...
Tokyo's Gate.
東京的後門
[CLOSER'S JOURNAL]
【閉門師日記】
Perhaps Daijin is trying to open that door once more.
或許大臣是想要再次打開那扇門
It's no use...
沒用了...
The information has been blotted out.
細節都被塗黑了
Why?
為什麼？
Is the location a secret?
位置是秘密嗎？
I've gotta ask Grandpa.
我要去問爺爺
Grandpa?
爺爺?
He pretty much raised me.
我是他帶大的
He's in a hospital nearby.
現在他在附近的醫院
I didn't want to disappoint him...
我不想這樣去見他
looking like this.
讓他感到失望
Souta, you in there?
草太，你在嗎？
I know you are.
我知道你在裡面
- The window's open. - It's Serizawa.
- 窗戶開著呢 - 是芹澤
Of all the times...
來的真是時候...
Wh-Who?
是誰？
Someone I know.
我的朋友
Just make him go away.
隨便把他打發走
Souta! I'm opening the door, dude.
草太！我要自己開門了
I'm coming in.
我要進來了
I warned ya.
我先聲明了
He's a good guy.
他是個好人
Hello.
你好
Um, and you are?
你...是誰？
His younger sister.
草太的妹妹
He's got a sister?
他有妹妹？
Well... A cousin who's LIKE a younger sister, really.
這個嘛...是像妹妹的表妹
What?
什麼？
Umm...
呃...
You're Serizawa, right?
芹澤，對嗎？
Teacher employment exam?
教師招聘考試？
Yeah.
嗯
Yesterday was the second one, but he didn't show up.
昨天是第二次考試，他卻沒出席
He had a test yesterday?
昨天有考試？
What an idiot...
真是個笨蛋
[TEACHER EMPLOYMENT EXAM PREP] Four years right down the drain.
【教師招聘考試參考】 四年時間就這樣浪費了
It bothered me so much, I couldn't focus on my test.
我也心煩的無法專注考試
Say, you...
你叫...
Suzume, was it?
鈴芽，對嗎？
When you get a hold of Souta,
如果你看到草太
tell him that I'm pissed, and that he's dead to me.
告訴他不要再出現在我面前
Ah, wait.
不過，等一下
He owes me 20,000 yen.
他還欠我兩萬元
I want that first.
告訴他把錢還給我
I heard his family business was in trouble and all...
聽說他的家族生意出了問題
But, he doesn't take care of himself enough.
他又是個生活白痴
Ticks me off.
想了就生氣
See ya.
再見了
[EARTHQUAKE WARNING]
【地震警報】
Is there gonna be a quake?
有地震嗎？
Hey, what are you--?
你想做什麼？
It stopped...
停止了
You okay?
你還好嗎？
It's close.
就在這裡附近
Whoa, that's a lot of birds.
哇，好多小鳥
Let's go.
我們走吧
Yeah.
嗯
Hey, where are you going?
等一下，你要去哪裡？
I had no idea.
我完全不知情...
About your test!
你居然有考試
What do we do?
現在該怎麼辦？
It's not your fault!
這不是你的錯！
But it's all because I freed the Keystone!
都是因為我把要石拔出來！
We put an end to it today.
今天就來做個了斷吧
We return the cat to the Keystone, and I become human again.
把貓變回要石，我也能恢復原樣
What's going on?
這是怎麼回事？
There's so many birds!
好多小鳥！
Because of the earthquake?
是地震造成的嗎？
Hey, where's the Gate!?
後門在哪裡？
Yeah.
那裡
Looks like it's downriver.
河流的下方
Oh my.
天啊
A cat?
貓咪？
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Let's play.
我們一起玩吧
Daijin!
大臣！
H-Hey--!
等等！
What was that?
剛才的是什麼？
A chair!?
椅子！？
- Did you see that? - What was it?
- 你有看到嗎？ - 那是什麼？
What?
什麼？
Daijin!
大臣！
Return to the Keystone!
快變回要石！
One is not enough!
一顆的力量是不夠的！
Nope.
不行
Why!?
為什麼！？
You still don't get it?
你還不懂嗎？
Where'd you go!?
它去了哪裡？
Souta?
草太？
Tokyo's Gate is...
東京的後門...
down there?
在那裡？
How do we even get there!?
要怎樣去那裡！？
It stopped?
停住了？
No.
並沒有
What the...?
怎麼回事？
It's no use...
來不及了...
[Earthquake warning]
【地震警報】
The warning stopped.
警報停止了
What's going on?
這是怎麼回事？
The second Keystone...
第二顆要石...
It couldn't hold it.
鎮壓不住了
The whole body is coming out!
地龍要完全掙脫了！
Daijin!?
大臣!?
We WILL prevent a major earthquake.
我們一定要阻止地震發生
Suzume.
鈴芽
I'm going.
我非去不可
You can't be serious!
不可以！
Souta!
草太！
Hey, is that...?
你看那裡！
Wait!
等等我！
Wha--!?
天啊！？
Suzume!?
鈴芽！？
What's going on?
這是怎麼回事？
What's that?
那是什麼？
Something's weird...
好奇怪...
Are you crazy!?
你瘋了嗎！？
But...
可是...
Suzume!!
鈴芽！
I'm coming!
我來救你！
Souta?
草太？
The surface is unstable.
地龍的表面不穩定
Don't let go.
不要放手比較好
Okay.
嗯
[EARTHQUAKE EPICENTER THE 23 DISTRICTS]
【地震震源東京23區】
The worm...
地龍...
is covering the city.
逐漸掩蓋著整個城市
Souta!
草太！
I know!
只好這樣了！
We need to pierce it with the Keystone...
我們利用要石鎮住它...
with Daijin.
也就是需要大臣
Suzume!
鈴芽！
When the worm falls...
地龍一旦墜落...
the earth will break.
就會產生地震
Daijin!
大臣！
Souta?
草太？
What's the matter?
怎麼了？
A lot of people...
從現在開始…
are about to die.
有很多人即將死去
Why would you let that happen!?
你為什麼要這樣做？
Become the Keystone again!
快變回要石！
Can't.
不行
I'm no longer the Keystone.
我已經不是要石了
You are the Keystone.
你才是要石
Hey!
這個...
What should we do, Souta?
草太，我們應該怎麼做？
Souta?
草太？
Suzume... I'm sorry.
鈴芽...對不起
I finally understand.
我終於明白了
I didn't realize...
我一直沒有發現
or maybe didn't want to.
或許是我不想面對現實
Um, Souta?
草太？
Your body...
你的身體...
Now...
現在...
It's freezing!
好冷！
I am...
我就是...
the Keystone.
要石
The moment I became a chair,
從我變成椅子的瞬間
the role of a Keystone was passed on to me.
我就變成了要石
That can't be...
不會的...
This is it...
是的...
This is where I end?
這就是我的結束？
Souta?
草太？
But, I was able to meet you.
不過，能夠遇見你...
Souta? Souta!?
草太？草太！？
Hey! Souta!
草太！
SOUTA!?
草太!？
That's not Souta anymore.
他已經不是草太了
Daijin...
大臣...
How dare you--!
你怎麼可以...!
Aren't you going to stick that into the worm?
你要用它插入地龍嗎？
How could I!?
我怎麼可以!?
The worm's gonna fall.
如果地龍墜落
The earth will break.
就會產生地震
It's falling...
它要掉下來了...
Souta!
草太！
Please, wake up!
拜託你快醒過來！
That's not Souta anymore!
他已經不是草太了
Souta, wake up!
草太，快醒過來！
What am I supposed to do?
我應該怎麼做?
Souta!?
草太！？
SOUTA!
草太!？
Lots'a people are gonna die.
有很多人即將死去
History will repeat...
歷史將會重演
I don't...
我不要...
I never wanted this...
我不想這麼做...
How can this...!?
不行！？
Hey, look at that!
你看那個！
Wow!
哇！
Aurora?
是極光嗎？
Rainbow at night?
夜晚出現彩虹？
Beautiful...
好美...
Mommy!
媽媽！
Is it ready yet?
還沒好嗎？
Not even close.
還沒呢
Now?
好了嗎？
Not yet.
還沒
Hmm, almost?
還差一點
Nooow!?
還沒好嗎？
Let's see...
讓我看看...
Here you go!
完成了！
Happy birthday, Suzume.
鈴芽，祝你生日快樂
Whoooa.
哇
Hey, is its face here?
它的臉是在這裡嗎？
What?
什麼？
This is a chair.
這是一張椅子
Just for you.
我特別為你做的
How's that?
如何？
A chair for me!
我的專屬椅子！
Thank you, Mommy!
媽媽，謝謝你！
I'm gonna keep it
我一定會珍惜它…
forever and ever!
一輩子！
Forever?
一輩子？
Well, thank goodness I built it for you.
太好了，不枉費我的心力
[MAY 24: TODAY MY MOM BUILT ME A CHAIR...]
【5月24日：媽媽給我做了一張椅子】
How long...
究竟過了多久...
did I actually care for it?
它還在我的心中嗎？
Where...
這裡...
...am I?
是哪裡？
Souta?
草太？
Is this...?
這裡是...
Tokyo's Gate!?
東京的後門？
Souta!?
草太！？
I can't get in.
我進不去
He's in the Ever-After.
他已經去了常世
Souta.
草太
Souta?
草太？
Souta!
草太！
SOUTA!
草太!
Suzume?
鈴芽？
Finally, just the two of us!
我們終於在一起了！
This is all your fault!
都是你的錯！
Give me Souta back!
把草太還給我！
Can't.
不行
Why?
為什麼？
He's not human anymore.
他已經不是人類了
Then make him human!
那你把他變回來！
Suzume, that hurts.
鈴芽，好疼啊
Bring him BACK!
把他變回來！
I said that hurts!
我說了，好疼啊！
You--!
你這個...
You don't love me?
你不喜歡我了嗎？
How could I--!?
我怎麼可能...
You love me, right?
你喜歡我吧？
I HATE--!
我討厭你...!
Go away.
你走吧
Don't ever talk to me again.
我不想跟你說話
Suzume doesn't love me...
你...不喜歡我了
I promise, I'll come save you.
我發誓我一定會把你救出來
I return to you...
全部奉還於你...
What--!?
那是什麼!?
Hey, look at that girl.
你看那女孩
She's not wearing any shoes.
她光著腳丫子
You're right. Ew.
真的，好邋遢
Just look at her clothes.
你看那女孩
That girl over there.
穿著破爛的衣服
Is she barefoot?
還沒穿鞋子呢
For real?
怎麼這樣？
Munakata's condition has stabilized.
宗像的情況穩定了不少
Yeah, it was pretty bad yesterday.
嗯，昨天還不怎麼樂觀
[HITSUJIRO MUNAKATA] Souta's...
【宗像羊朗】 草太的...
Souta failed, didn't he?
草太失敗了吧？
I-I'm sorry for barging in...
不好意思打擾了
I heard from Souta that you were in the hospital.
草太說他爺爺在醫院
Did he drag you into this?
你是被他牽連的吧？
What is the fate of my grandson?
我的孫子怎樣了？
He became a Keystone and went to the Ever-After...
他變成了要石，去了常世
I see.
果然如此
I saw the worm from my window yesterday.
昨天我從窗戶看到了地龍
I wanted nothing more than to go myself...
我也想挺身而出
but this old body of mine wouldn't listen.
可是，這副老骨頭就是不聽使喚
That's why I want to know how to enter the Ever-After.
我來是想要知道如何去常世
Why?
為什麼？
Huh? Because... we have to save Souta!
蛤？因為我要去救草太！
That isn't necessary.
沒這個必要
What?
什麼？
Souta will spend decades now
從其以後，草太就會...
as a Keystone housing the gods.
變成守護神明的要石
He is no longer of our realm.
他已經不屬於這個世界了
How could...
怎麼可以...
But there must be a way to--
一定有辦法的...
Are you trying to waste my grandson's sacrifice?
你想枉費我孫子的犧牲嗎？
What?
什麼？
Who is the one who pierced the worm?
是誰用要石鎮住了地龍？
Did you, with Souta?
不是你用草太...
But that was...
那是因為...
ANSWER ME!
回答我！
It was me!
是我！
I see.
既然如此
That's fine!
那就好
If you didn't, millions would have died!
如果不那麼做就會死很多人
Take pride in your deed, keep your mouth shut,
現在功德圓滿，不要再插嘴
and return to whence you came!
回去你該去的地方！
This world is not for the ordinary.
這不是凡夫俗子能插手的
Forget everything that happened.
把一切忘了吧
How could I forget?
我怎麼可以忘記？
I'll open the underground Gate again.
我要再次打開地下的後門
What!? What are you saying?
什麼!? 你在說什麼？
I have to get in!
我一定要進去！
Impossible.
絕對不行
You cannot enter it there!
你不可以進去！
You mustn't open the Gate!
絕對不能打開後門！
Wait!
等一下！
The Ever-After is a beautiful place.
雖然常世擁有絕世美景
But it is the domain of the departed.
但是那是屬於亡者的領域
Does that not scare you?
難道你不害怕嗎？
It doesn't.
我不怕
Whether one lives or dies is a matter of luck.
生與死只是一線之差
I've always felt that way.
我一直都這麼認為
But...
可是...
I'm afraid of a world without Souta.
我更害怕沒有草太的世界!
There is but one Gate through which people may traverse in their lifetime.
每個人在一生中都有一次機會穿越後門
You've been to the Ever-After before, no?
你去過常世嗎？
What did you see there?
你在那裡看到了什麼？
That was...
我看到了...
A young version of myself.
小時候的自己
And, my mom...who passed away.
還有，往生的母親
I suspect you got lost in the Ever-After when you were young.
幼小的你應該是在常世里迷路了
You must find THAT Gate. From back then.
你要找到那時候的那扇門
It has been far too long.
好久不見
I see you are finally unbound.
你終於自由了
Do you wish to follow that girl?
你要跟著那女孩嗎？
I entrust everything to you.
一切就拜託你了
I'm borrowing your shoes, Souta.
草太，讓我穿你的鞋子
Hey!
喂！
Hey, you!
我在叫你呢...
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Serizawa?
芹澤？
Where are you going?
你要去哪裡？
To find Souta?
找草太嗎？
To find a door.
我要去找一扇門
What?
什麼？
Sorry, I'm in a hurry.
對不起，我在趕時間
Hey, I looked everywhere for you!
喂，我好不容易才找到你！
What are--
你想做什麼...
The cousin thing's a lie, right?
草太的表妹，是騙人的吧？
Why does it matter?
管你什麼事！
- Get in. - What?
- 上車 - 你想幹嘛？
You're going after Souta, right?
你要去找草太，不是嗎？
Then, I'll take you.
讓我帶你去
Why would you--!?
不管你的事
I'm worried about my friend, okay!?
我在擔心朋友，不行嗎？
- What's that? - A fight?
- 他們在做什麼？ - 吵架嗎？
There you are!
找到你了！
Suzume!!
鈴芽！
W-What? Tamaki?
欸！阿姨？
Do you have ANY idea how worried I've been!?
太好了，你知道我多擔心你嗎？
And you! You stay away from her.
還有你！不要接近她
Or I'll call the police.
不然，我就報警
Who're you?
這是誰？
Is this the guy who came to our house?
是這傢伙來過我們的家？
Whatever he told you is a lie.
不要被他騙了
We're going.
我們回去吧
I'm sorry, but I can't yet.
對不起，我還不能走
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Serizawa, let's go.
芹澤，快開車
O-Okay.
好的
H-Hey!
喂！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
What the heck is wrong with you!?
你有什麼問題？
I can't let you go alone.
我不能讓你一個人跟他走
- Tamaki, get out. - Come here, Suzume.
- 阿姨，你快下車 - 鈴芽，你過來
This car has doors, you know!
為什麼要爬進車子！
Is he two-timing?
是三角關係嗎？
Men are such pigs.
男人就是賤!
- Yeah, and you ignored them! - Let's all calm dow--
- 你都是已讀不回！ - 我們冷靜下來
Are you guys...
你們...
done yet?
吵夠了嗎？
- Daijin? - A cat spoke!?
- 大臣！ - 貓咪會說話？
What? Of course not...
什麼？當然不會
Yeah, you're right.
你說得對
Sure, cats don't talk.
貓咪怎麼可能說話
More importantly...
現在要緊的是...
[Destination confirmed.] - Serizawa, can you take us here?
【確定目的地】 - 芹澤，你能帶我們去這裡嗎？
W-Whaaat!? This is far!
什麼！？這地方也太遠了！
Suzume, isn't this...?
鈴芽，這裡不是...
You said you would take me, didn't you?
你不是說去哪裡都行嗎？
Please, I have to go there.
拜託，我一定要去那裡
Seriously...?
不會吧？
Guess we're not comin' back tonight...
我想今晚是回不來了
What are you trying to pull?
你到底想做什麼？
♪ In order to see his mom...
♪為了要見他的媽媽...
♪ I boarded the train all on my own!
♪我獨自一人搭上了列車...
♪ ...the twilit cityscape and cars passing by
♪夕陽的街道和過往的車輛...
♪ I watched out the corner of my eye.
♪從我眼角擦身而過
Do you mind?
吵死了！
What? This is the perfect road trip song.
什麼？這是兜風的最佳歌曲
And we have a cat...
還有一隻貓陪著
Suzume's not listening.
鈴芽又沒在聽
She's asleep.
她已經睡著了
Hey, is that cat hers?
貓咪是她養的嗎？
We don't have any cats.
我們家裡沒有養貓
Serizawa...
芹澤...
You're a teacher in training?
你正準備要當教師？
Um, yeah...
對啊
I wanna become one.
我想要當教師
Is this car okay?
這輛車沒問題嗎？
It's used. I got it super cheap.
是二手車，非常便宜
Cool, huh?
很帥吧？
Are you sure you want to do this?
你真的要去嗎？
It's more than seven hours one way.
單程可需要要七小時
Your daughter's not the only one looking for Souta.
不只是你女兒一人在找草太
She's not my daughter...
她不是我的女兒...
She's my niece.
鈴芽是我的侄女
My older sister passed away, so I took her in.
我姐姐去世了，所以我收養了她
She was a single mom.
她沒有爸爸
I see.
原來如此
Back then, Suzume was only four.
當時的鈴芽只有四歲
She couldn't process her mother disappearing so suddenly...
不能理解母親突然的離世
and got lost trying to search for her.
一直想要找媽媽，還迷路了呢
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Suzume, where are you?
鈴芽，你在哪裡？
- Auntie? - Everything's all right now.
- 阿姨？ - 沒事了
I'm so sorry it took me so long to find you.
對不起，花了這麼久才找到你
Starting today, you're my daughter, okay?
從今天開始，你就是我的女兒
It's been 12 years since that day.
一轉眼就過了十二年
I took her with me to Kyushu, and we've lived together ever since.
我把她帶到九州，就一直住在一起
Oh, do you mind the smoke?
你介意我抽菸嗎？
It's your car.
我才不管，反正是你的車
So, we're headed for Suzume's hometown then?
所以，我們要去鈴芽的故鄉嗎？
Is Souta really gonna be there?
草太會在那裡嗎？
I don't know...
不知道...
But there's nothing left there.
可是，那裡什麼都沒有
Say, why don't we head back to Tokyo?
不如我們回東京吧？
That'll make her give up.
這樣，她就會死心了
Souta owes me money, and I need it back.
我也想跟草太要回我的錢
So you're a loan shark now?
你現在也放高利貸？
♪ And she'll be so mad at you, my darling!
♪全部都發洩在我身上吧，我的愛人！
[CONTAMINATED SOIL]
【廢棄土壤】
[EVACUATION ZONE AHEAD]
【限制通行】
♪ I guess it's the pain that brings back those memories
♪那些傷痛 真讓人懷念
♪ All of the ones that I Thought were all dead and gone
♪直到現在 我已經忘記
Did you just feel something shake?
你剛才感覺到搖晃嗎？
Look who decided to join us.
你終於醒了
Now your aunt's asleep.
現在輪到阿姨睡著了
Does your family not know how to sleep?
你們全家都缺乏睡眠嗎？
[EARTHQUAKE WARNING INTENSITY 3.0]
【地震警報強度3級】
You're right. I didn't realize it.
真的，開著車子都沒注意
Stop!
停下來！
Hey, wa--!
等一下！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
It's not appearing.
還沒有出現
Souta must be containing it.
肯定是草太在抑制它
Daijin...
大臣...
What are you trying to do?
你到底想要什麼？
Why won't you say anything?
為什麼一言不語？
Hey, can anyone...
我問你，是不是任何人...
become a Keystone?
都可以成為要石？
Not just Closers?
而不只是閉門師？
Heeey!
喂！
Suzume.
鈴芽
What's up with you?
你怎麼了？
Sorry, it's nothing.
對不起，我沒事
Gotta hurry.
我們還得趕路
We're about halfway now.
路途已經過了一半
I didn't know this area was so beautiful.
我從沒發現這裡如此美麗
This place is...beautiful?
這裡...美麗？
Sorry, we need to get going.
對不起，我們應該走了
Hey.
喂
Hey, you...
喂，我叫你呢
Cat!
貓咪！
Man...
這一家人...
Your family's got some serious issues...
好像都有問題
♪ What is it you're looking for?
♪你在找尋什麼？
♪ Something hard to find?
♪是不是一件難以尋獲的東西？
♪ In your bag, through your desk
♪在你的書包裡，在桌子的抽屜裡
♪ you looked but can't find it.
♪儘管翻了幾遍還是都找不到
♪ Do you want to keep searching?
♪你還想繼續尋找嗎？
♪ Why not dance with me instead?
♪不如放棄與我跳舞吧？
♪ Into our dreams, on into our dreams.
♪一起進入夢鄉，一起環遊夢境
♪ Wouldn't you rather roam a bit?
♪難道你不想和我一起流浪嗎？
Rain?
下雨了？
Seriously?
真的嗎？
Well, that's not good...
糟了...
Why? You have a roof, don't you?
怎麼了？你的敞篷跑車有頂蓋吧？
Just close it.
快把它關上
Let's give it a go.
讓我來試試
Hey...
什麼...
Yep, still broken.
果然還沒修好
Haha.
哈哈
Don't "Haha" me!
這有什麼好笑的！
How're you gonna fix this!?
你快想辦法!
No worries.
別擔心
We're almost to the next rest stop.
很快就到下一個休息站了
[Approximately 40km to your destination. ETA 35 minutes.]
【距離下一站還有40公里35分鐘車程】
Almost, my foot!
根本就還很遠！
[OYA KAIGAN - REST STOP] The time is 3:30PM.
【大谷海岸休息站】 時間是3點30分
Thanks for the grub!
我要開動了！
What?
什麼？
You're with some shady playboy?
他是牛郎嗎？
Well, more like a discount hustler,
比較像是窮酸的皮條客
but I don't think he's up to anything.
應該不是什麼壞人
That's super dangerous!
那也太危險了！
It's just you two girls.
何況只有你們兩個女生
A closed car's dangerous!
車子裡密閉空間太危險了！
Well, it's a convertible.
是敞篷跑車
That's even worse!
那更慘！
- Tamaki, where in Miyagi are you now? - Tamaki again?
- 小環，你說你在宮城哪裡？ - 又是小環嗎？
- Wait one sec. - Minoru doesn't give up, does he?
- 等一下 - 阿稔還真是死纏爛打
There's a bus at that rest stop headed for Tokyo.
那個休息站有前往東京的巴士
And there are open seats.
現在還有位子
I can book 'em right now.
我這裡可以幫你預約
Just hold up, Minoru.
阿稔，你別著急
We've come quite a ways...
好不容易來到了這裡
I don't think that...
如果現在回去...
[EARTHQUAKE WARNING INTENSITY 3.0]
【地震警報強度3級】
Souta.
草太
Souta...
草太...
Suzume, it just shook again, huh?
鈴芽，剛才又有地震了吧？
There are so many earthquakes lately.
最近地震還真多
Hey, you sure you don't want anything to eat?
你真的不要吃嗎？
Yup.
嗯
Suzume...
鈴芽...
Could you tell me?
你能告訴我...
What?
什麼？
Why are you so hell-bent on returning home?
為什麼你一定要回去故鄉嗎？
A door...
後門...
Sorry, it's hard to explain.
抱歉，有點難以啟齒
What's that mean?
是什麼意思？
After all the trouble you've caused!
你已經闖了那麼多禍！
Trouble?
闖禍？
You wouldn't understand anyway, Tamaki.
跟你說了，你也不會明白
That's it. We're taking that bus home.
我們回去，這裡有回程的巴士
You won't tell me anything.
反正你什麼都不說
You look depressed.
又一直鬱鬱寡歡
You won't eat.
飯也不吃
Let me go!
放開我！
Suzume!
鈴芽！
You go home, Tamaki!
阿姨，你自己回去！
I never asked you to come after me!
我沒讓你來找我！
Do you have any idea!?
難道你不知道嗎？
I was worried sick!
我是多麼的擔心你！
That's exactly why I'm suffocating!
所以，你才讓我喘不過氣！
I can't...take this anymore.
我也忍無可忍了
I had to take you in.
為了收養你
I devoted the last 10 years to you.
我付出了十年的時間
I'm such an idiot...
我真是愚蠢...
Every day I walk on eggshells.
每天都小心翼翼的
A child who lost her mother?
為了不讓你觸景傷情
I could never have anyone over because of you.
因為你，我都不能請人來家裡
And who would marry someone who's basically got a kid?
誰會要一個帶著小孩的女人？
Even with my sister's money, there's no balancing that scale.
就算有姐姐的遺產，那又怎樣！
Is that...?
是這樣的嗎？
But it's not like I...
可是，我也是...
"Sorry it took me so long..."
“對不起，這麼久才找到你...”
had a choice, either.
別無選擇
"You're my daughter..."
“你就是我的女兒...”
You're the one who said, "You're my daughter"!
是你說的，“你就是我的女兒！”
I don't remember that.
我不記得了
Get out of my house.
滾出我的家
Give me back my life!
把我的生活還給我！
Who... are you?
你是誰？
Sadaijin.
左大臣
Sadaijin...?
左大臣？
H-Hey, Tamaki?
阿姨?
What happened!?
發生了什麼事？
Are you okay?
阿姨，你還好嗎？
What did I...?
我...
Sorry, I have to--!
對不起，我...
Serizawa.
芹澤
Yeah?
怎麼了？
I think I'm losing it...
我好像快瘋了
Why would I say something like that?
我怎麼會說出那種話？
Uh...
什麼...
Hey, hey, hey!
等一下！
Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
Yup... Seriously big issues.
果然... 這家人問題不輕
♪ I took the button on my uniform...
♪ 制服上的鈕扣...
Nope.
不是這首
♪ A Valentine's day kiss!
♪ 情人節的吻!
Not this.
也不是這首
[STOP FIGHTING]
【不要吵架】
There ya go.
就是這首
♪ Please stop the fighting, both of you...
♪ 不要再吵了,你們都停下來...
♪ I don't want you two... to fight over me
♪ 我不想你們為了我而爭吵
This car's pretty great when it's sunny, right?
晴朗的天氣，敞篷跑車很棒吧？
Umm... Do you mind?
呃...煩死了！
Huh?
蛤？
I'm choosing the songs that suit my audience.
我是選擇適合乘客的歌曲
You appreciate the oldies, right, Suzume?
鈴芽，你也喜歡老歌嗎？
Guess the rain ain't done yet...
看來氣氛還很僵
Right, newcomer?
對吧，新來的?
How did we pick up another stray?
什麼時候多了一隻貓？
And a huge one, at that.
還這麼大一隻
Hey, a rainbow.
前面有彩虹
Now there's a good sign.
看來是好預兆
Man.
真是的
Tough crowd.
我是在對牛彈琴
Suzume, cats don't follow people without a reason.
鈴芽，貓咪不會無緣無故跟著人類
Unlike dogs.
貓跟狗不一樣
Those black and white cats...
這兩隻貓...
must really want something from you.
肯定是有求於你
Precisely.
你說中了
Wha--!?
欸！？
Return everything as it was, with human hands.
用你的雙手，還原所有一切
It spoke!
貓咪會說話！
Ah...hey, hey, he--
不好了...
You're kidding me...
不是真的吧...
Hey, it's fixed.
啊，關上了
Oh, come on!
不是吧！
That could've ended much worse.
已經是不幸中的萬幸了
Never mind that. Did those cats just talk?
話說那兩隻貓真的說話了，對嗎？
T-They totally did, didn't they?
真的說話了吧？
What the heck was that?
到底是怎麼回事？
Supernatural stuff?
靈異現象嗎？
Nah, that can't be possible.
應該沒有可能
Excuse me!
不好意思！
They won't stop.
車子都不停
Serizawa!
芹澤
We're about 10km out, right?
還有10公里，對嗎？
[Approximately 20km to your destination.]
【距離目的地還有20公里】
More like 20.
好像還有20公里
It's still quite a ways away.
還有一段路程
[Return to the designated route.]
【重啟新路線】
I KNOW!
我知道了！
I'm gonna run the rest.
剩餘的路程，讓我自己來
Thank you so much, Serizawa!
謝謝你，芹澤！
You too, Tamaki!
還有你，阿姨！
I'm going too.
芹澤，我也跟著去
Thanks for getting us this far.
謝謝你帶我們來到這裡
I think you might actually make a great teacher...
或許你將來會成為一位好老師
H-Hey, you guys...!
等一下，你們兩個！
What the heck was that all about?
她們兩個到底怎麼了？
Man, I envy you, Souta.
草太這小子，真令人羨慕
Tamaki?
阿姨？
I give up.
我明白了
This is about you chasing someone you love, right?
你要去找喜歡的人，對嗎？
Th-This isn't a love thing.
沒什麼喜歡不喜歡的
Hey, Suzume...
鈴芽...
Who are these guys?
它們到底是什麼東西？
They're supposed to be gods?
聽說是天上的神仙？
Gods!?
神仙！？
What I said, in the parking lot...
我在停車場說的那番話...
Sure, I've felt that way at times...
我確實那樣想過
But that's not the only thing I've felt.
可是也並非如此而已
Yeah.
嗯
You understand it's not the only thing...
你知道的並非如此而已
Me too.
我也是
I'm sorry, Tamaki.
對不起，阿姨
Your first time home in 12 years.
這是你十二年後第一次回鄉
I'm home, Mommy!
媽媽，我回來了!
I'm home, Mom.
媽媽，我回來了
Look at how much she's grown, Sis.
姐姐，鈴芽長大了不少
I have no idea what she's about to do.
她究竟想要做什麼呢?
Found it.
找到了
[SUZUME'S IMPORTANT STUFF]
【鈴芽的重要物品】
A diary?
日記？
Yeah.
嗯
I don't remember exactly what happened back then.
當時的事情，我不是很清楚
But, I do remember wandering through a door...
可是，我記得我穿過了一扇門
[MARCH 11]
【3月11日】
[Tsunami warning.]
【海嘯警報】
[Those near the ocean, please evacuate to high ground immediately.]
【沿海的居民，請立刻到高處避難】
Have you seen my mommy?
你有看到我媽媽嗎？
- Are you alone? - She was working at the hospital.
- 你一個人嗎？ - 她還在醫院工作
Have you seen my mommy?
你有看到我媽媽嗎？
- They haven't found Tsubame? - That girl's still looking today.
- 還沒有找到樁芽嗎？ - 那女孩今天也來找媽媽
Do you know where my mommy is?
你知道我媽媽在哪裡嗎？
- She's only four... - Her mother's probably--
- 她只有四歲... - 或許她媽媽已經...
- The poor thing. - Have you seen my mommy...?
- 好可憐啊 - 你有看到我媽媽嗎？
She's all alone.
留下她孤零零的
- I'm sorry, Suzume. - My mommy...!
- 對不起，鈴芽 - 媽媽！
Sorry.
真不好意思
Mommy...!
媽媽！
Where are you?
你在哪裡？
It wasn't...a dream.
那不是一場夢
That's right, the moon was full that night.
對了，那晚正好是滿月
Right by that telephone pole.
月亮就在電線杆那裡
What?
什麼？
You're looking for this door?
你在找這扇門嗎？
Hey, Suzume!
喂，鈴芽！
It's been 12 years! The rubble's probably long gone!
過了十二年！或許已經不在了
Where...?
在哪裡？
Suzume.
鈴芽
Daijin?
大臣？
Hey, what're...?
等一下，你...？
Daijin, have you...?
大臣，難道你...
Have you been guiding us to the open doors all this time?
是你一直領導我們去後門的嗎？
This whole time...
一直都是你...
Whoa...!
啊...
Thank you so much, Daijin!
謝謝你，大臣
Let's go, Suzume!
我們走吧，鈴芽
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Tamaki.
阿姨
I'm going!
我要走了
Going where?
你要去哪裡？
To see the person I love!
去找我喜歡的人！
Suzume...?
鈴芽
The ground is on fire.
地面上著火了
That's...
那個是...
The worm!
地龍!
It's going for the Gate!
它正往後門飛去！
Sadaijin?
左大臣？
Is that...?
那個是...?
Souta!?
草太？
Daijin, you...!
大臣，你...
Suzume, are you okay?
鈴芽，你沒事吧？
What is this place?
這是什麼地方？
This is the Ever-After?
這裡就是常世嗎?
It's Souta!
是草太！
Souta!
草太！
SOUTA!
草太!
Suzume.
鈴芽
If you take the Keystone,
如果你把要石拔出來
the worm will escape.
地龍就會逃出去的
I'll become the Keystone!
那就讓我變成要石!
So please...
拜託你...
Wake up, Souta!
草太，快醒過來！
You...
大臣...
Souta!
草太！
I've come this far!
我好不容易來到這裡!
Please, answer me!
快說話,草太!
Souta!
草太！
Let me hear your voice.
讓我聽見你的聲音
SOUTA!
草太!
Hey, you...
喂，我叫你呢
Do you know of any ruins in this area?
你知道附近有沒有廢墟？
Ruins...?
廢墟？
Are you not afraid to die!?
你不怕死嗎？
I'm not!
我不怕！
We make a great team!
我們太厲害了！
I think I'm doing something pretty important!
我也覺得我正在做一件大事！
Join us.
你也一起吧
Well, aren't you popular, Souta?
草太，你很受歡迎吧？
Wait!
等一下！
Is this...?
這個是...
Yeah.
嗯
This is it...
是的...
This is where I end?
這就是我的結束？
Souta's memories?
草太的記憶?
- Souta? - But, I was able to meet you.
- 草太？ - 不過，能夠遇見你...
- Souta!
- 草太！
Hey! Souta!
喂！草太！
I finally met you!
我終於遇見了你!
SOUTA!
草太!
I don't want to disappear.
我不要消失
I want to live!
我要活下去!
I want to keep living!
我要一直活下去!
I'm afraid to die!
我不要死!
I want to live.
我要活下去
To live...
活下去...
To live.
活下去
More!
我要活下去!
So do I!
我也是!
I want to live more...
我要活下去
I want to hear your voice.
想聽見你的聲音
I don't want to be alone.
我不要孤身一人
I'm afraid to die.
我不要死
Souta...
草太...
Souta...?
草太...?
Suzume?
鈴芽？
What was I...?
我怎麼了?
Daijin?
大臣
What's wrong?
你怎麼了？
You okay?
你還好嗎？
I...
我...
couldn't become your cat, Suzume.
不能成為你的寵物了
Return me...
請用你的雙手...
...with your hands.
把我歸還回去
Daijin...
大臣...
The second Keystone...!
第二顆要石...
The worm's going to escape from the Gate!
地龍要逃出後門了!
Suzume!
鈴芽！
I'm fine.
我沒事
What now?
現在應該怎麼辦？
Hear their voices, and they'll hear us.
專心傾聽,他們也會聽見的
Follow me!
跟我來!
O Divine Gods who dwell beneath this land...
令人敬畏的神明啊
You have long protected us for generations...
古老的祖先之地啊
Thy mountains and rivers that we have long called our own...
請容許我把您恩賜的山河
We respectfully return to thee!
全部都奉還於你！
"Morning!"
“早安”
"Bon appetit!"
“我要開動了”
"Thanks for the food."
“我吃飽了”
"I'll see you later!"
“稍後見”
"See you soon."
“路上小心”
"Come home soon."
“早點回來”
- "See you later!" - "Come home soon."
- “我出門了” - “路上小心”
- "I'm off now." - "Take care."
- “我要走了” - “小心一點”
- "See you later." - "Come home soon."
- “我出門了” - “路上小心”
- "Don't be too late." - "I'll see you soon."
- “早點回來” -“稍後見”
- "Take care!" - "See you soon."
- “小心一點” - “路上小心”
"See you later."
“我出門了”
I know that life is fleeting.
我知道生命是短暫的
We live side-by-side with death.
我們都活在生死邊緣
Even then...
即使是一年...
once more...
就算是一天...
even for just one moment more
還是只有一剎那
we wish to live!
我們都想要活下去!
Divine gods...!
令人敬畏的神明啊...
Please... Please!
我請求您...我請求您!
I beg of you!
償我所願!
It's okay.
沒事的
Entrust yourself.
相信自己
I return to you!!
全部都奉還於你！
Suzume...
鈴芽...
Suzume, there's someone here...
鈴芽，那裡有人
A child?
是個孩子?
That girl...
那個女孩...
I...need to go!
我要去找她!
Suzume?
鈴芽？
I see...
原來如此
That's right.
我知道了
I finally understand!
我終於明白了
Suzume.
鈴芽
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Mommy?
媽媽？
No...
不是的...
Do you know where my mommy is?
你知道我媽媽在哪裡嗎？
I know she's looking for me, too!
我知道她肯定在找我
And she must be super worried!
她也一定很擔心!
I need to go to where she is!
我要去找她!
Suzume, you're...
鈴芽...
My mommy works at the hospital,
我媽媽在醫院工作
and she's really good at cooking and wood stuff.
她擅長料理，還有木工
She can make anything!
為了我，她什麼都能做!
Suzume--!
鈴芽！
And my house is...
我的家...
It's gone, so...
沒有了,所以...
Mommy...
媽媽...
She just doesn't know where to look for me, so...!
她不知道要怎麼找我...
That's enough!!
夠了!
Deep down, I already knew...
我的心裡早就明白...
Why?
為什麼？
Mommy's still out there! She's looking for me!
媽媽還在…一直的找我!
Suzume!
鈴芽！
Mommy, where are you?
媽媽，你在哪裡？
MOMMY!!
媽媽！
Mom...
媽媽...
What am I supposed to do?
我應該怎麼做?
Suzume, look.
鈴芽，你看
See?
你看
It's my chair.
這是我的椅子
Huh?
為什麼？
How can I say this...
我應該怎麼說呢
You see, Suzume...
鈴芽...
No matter how sad you are now,
無論現在多麼痛徹心扉
you're going to grow up.
這是成長的必經過程
So, don't worry.
所以，你不用擔心
The future's not that scary.
未來充滿著希望
You'll meet a lot of people you care for...
你會遇見自己喜歡的人...
And you'll meet lots of people who'll care for you, too.
也會遇見喜歡你的人
The night might seem endless right now
雖然現在黑夜看似無窮無盡
but one day, morning will come.
但是黎明的曙光一定會來的
You'll grow up basking in that light.
你會在光明中長大成人
I'm sure of it.
我很肯定
It's written in the stars.
這一切都是命中注定
Miss...
姐姐...
who are you?
你是誰？
I'm...
我是...
your tomorrow.
你的明天
I completely forgot.
我徹底忘記了
I'd been given everything that matters a long time ago.
其實，我在以前已經擁有了最重要的東西
Okay, I'm off!
我要出發了!
♪ Meaning of love, the touch,
♪ 戀愛的意義，觸摸的手感
♪ the theory of relativity
♪ 還有相對的理論
♪ It all seems so unreal to me,
♪ 這些對我而言
- Suzume...! ♪ like a pipe dream in my mind
- 鈴芽 ♪ 都是不真實的幻想
- Hey!
- 嘿！
- Tamaki! ♪ like a pipe dream in my mind
- 阿姨！ ♪ 都是不真實的幻想
- Serizawa?
- 芹澤？
♪ By the time I grow up,
♪ 在長大成人的那個時候
- Say, did you get your money back from Souta? ♪ will we ever meet?
- 所以，草太把錢還給你了嗎? ♪ 我們是否能夠相遇呢
Oh, that... was a lie.
啊,那是我撒的謊
- I actually owe Souta. ♪ By then, will I know the meaning of
- 其實是我欠他的 ♪ 在那個時候，我們是否能理解
Looks like he forgot, so...
不過,他好像忘記了...
- Could you keep it between us? ♪ thousands of love songs?
- 你能幫我保密嗎? ♪ 萬千首情歌的意義呢
You're hopeless.
你真的是無可救藥
♪ But love was not a revolution or frustration or catastrophe
♪ 但是戀愛不是革命，不是焦慮，也不是天崩地裂
Why don't you come back with us?
為什麼你不跟我們回去?
- The weight of people's feelings is what quells the land. ♪ Love was you
- 思念的重量,能夠鎮壓住這片土地 ♪ 戀愛就是你
There are still places where that's disappeared, causing the Gates to open.
有些地方已經被人們遺忘了，促使後門被打開
I'll close them as I return to Tokyo.
回去東京的旅途中,我會把它們給關閉
♪ The way you laughed somehow resembled loneliness
♪ 你微笑的樣子不知為何形同寂寞
Souta! Um...
草太！我...
♪ The way you sang reminded me of a glow in this morning's sky
♪ 你歌唱的模樣喚起了早晨曙光的記憶
- Thank you for saving me. ♪ Rather than humans acting thousands of years from now
- 謝謝你的救命之恩 ♪ 比起能預知幾千年後人們的生活
- I'll come see you. I promise.
- 我一定會去找你的這是我們的約定
♪ I'd love to see you laugh with a face no one knows yet
♪ 我更想看見誰也未曾看過你的笑臉
♪ What I don't have, what I don't have is what you are made of
♪ 我沒有的，我沒有的是你所擁有的
♪ You make me who I am
♪ 是你讓我變成現在的模樣
♪ You're gonna laugh when I say this, right?
♪ 或許這些話語對你只是笑話
♪ I wanna see that face even
♪ 即使這樣，我也想看到你的笑臉
♪ What I don't have, what I don't have is what you are made of
♪ 我沒有的，我沒有的是你所擁有的
♪ And who the world sings praises to
♪ 我要對全世界宣告你的美好
♪ "If only you were here"
♪ “只要你在這裡”
[HOW TO BECOME A NURSE]
【如何成為一名護士】
♪ No matter how horrendous the words that follow may be
♪ 無論相繼的話語多麼的可怕不堪
♪ I'll embrace those words in my arms
♪ 我都會用雙臂緊緊擁抱著它
♪ Despair I see with you will shine brighter than the hope without you
♪ 比起沒有你的希望，與你共度的絕望將散發出更閃亮的光芒
Welcome back.
你回來了
♪ The way you laughed somehow resembled tenderness
♪ 你微笑的樣子不知為何形同溫柔
♪ The way you sang was like today's evening rain
♪ 你歌唱的模樣喚起了黃昏的驟雨
♪ Rather than humans acting thousands of years from now
♪ 比起能預知幾千年後人們的生活
♪ I'd love to see you laugh with a face no one knows yet
♪ 我更想看見誰也未曾看過你的笑臉
♪ What I don't have, what I don't have is what you are made of
♪ 我沒有的，我沒有的是你所擁有的
♪ You make me who I am
♪ 是你讓我變成現在的模樣
♪ If I call your name out till my voice is gone
♪ 我會聲嘶力竭叫喊著你的名字
♪ And if that's what it takes to reach you, then I will call right now
♪ 直到你能聽見我的聲音
♪ Red lines, blues lines you carry inside
♪ 你的身體裡面 紅色藍色長長的線
♪ The twain shall meet at the center of your heart
♪ 交織著對方彼此 相遇在你的心間
♪ In a voice that withstands the wind
♪ 風中的喧囂裡有 永不消逝 我的聲音
♪ I'm bringing up the words to deliver
♪ 我想要說的話語 如今孕育在腦海裡
♪ Time is a sleeper, wind the soft skin,
♪ 時間啊 平行交錯, 清風呀 吹過身邊
♪ the star is a cradle, people are a mirage
♪ 星辰啊 守護著我, 人們呀 如影如幻
♪ If this tear answers your question of why I'm crying
♪ 當你問我為何哭泣 我只能回答說 眼淚無法說明
♪ It's not as close to the meaning of us finding each other
♪ 當初我們為何相遇 其中有什麼意義 永遠都說不清
♪ It's the shout that this body alone will never be enough
♪ 單憑我一個人 吶喊遙不可及
♪ Found a heart that trembles only when I touch your hand
♪ 當我的手觸碰到你手時 我才能感覺到 心臟仍有悸動
♪ How many meanings must we get over to be there?
♪ 我們還需要跨越多少層面的意義 才能抵達終點
♪ Could be stupidity, could be ugliness,
♪ 就算愚蠢也好 即使醜陋也罷
♪ beyond what's right, I want to hold hands with you
♪ 往正確的彼端邁向前進 我想要牽著你的手
♪ Precious memories I can't recall
♪ 無法喚醒的 珍貴的過去記憶
♪ These are the thoughts that can't be put into words
♪ 無法言語的 這裡的以前往事
♪ Maybe, just maybe
♪ 亦或是如此，亦或是如此
♪ That's all this heart is made of
♪ 那些過往回憶造就了這顆心
♪ It still beats your heart
♪ 它還想要引起你的注意
♪ Wanting you to "notice me"
♪ 一直不停在你的胸口敲打著
♪ If this tear answers your question of why I'm crying
♪ 當你問我為何哭泣 我只能回答說 眼淚無法說明
♪ It's not as close to the meaning of us finding each other
♪ 當初我們為何相遇 其中有什麼意義 永遠都說不清
♪ It's the shout that this body alone will never be enough
♪ 單憑我一個人 吶喊遙不可及
♪ Found a heart that trembles only when I touch your hand
♪ 當我的手觸碰到你手時 我才能感覺到 心臟仍有悸動
♪ How many meanings must we get over to be there?
♪ 我們還需要跨越多少層面的意義 才能抵達終點
♪ Could be stupidity, could be ugliness,
♪ 就算愚蠢也好 即使醜陋也罷
♪ beyond what's right, I want to live with you
♪ 往正確的彼端邁向前進 我想要與你長相廝守